<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voyage to Virginia: or, The valliant souldier's farewel to his love. Unto Virginia he's resolv'd to go, she begs of him, that he would not do so; but her intreaties they are all in vain, for he must plow the curled ocean main: at length (with sorrow) he doth take his leave and leaves his dearest love at home to grieve. To the tune of, She's gone and left me here alone.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.8[580]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887987</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06480)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A5:2[450])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voyage to Virginia: or, The valliant souldier's farewel to his love. Unto Virginia he's resolv'd to go, she begs of him, that he would not do so; but her intreaties they are all in vain, for he must plow the curled ocean main: at length (with sorrow) he doth take his leave and leaves his dearest love at home to grieve. To the tune of, She's gone and left me here alone.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "My pritty Betty I now must leave thee ..."</note>
                  <note>Trimmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Love poetry, English --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soldiers --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ballads --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:183659:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>A Voyage to Virginia: OR, <hi>The Valliant Souldier's Farwel to his Love.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Unto <hi>Virginia</hi> he's reſolv'd to go,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She begs of him, that he would not do ſo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But her Intreaties they are all in vain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For he muſt plow the curled Ocean Main:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At length (with ſorrow) he doth take his leave</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And leaves his deareſt Love at home to grieve.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>She's gone and left me here alone.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>My pritty <hi>Betty</hi> I now muſt leave thée,</l>
               <l>the Drums doth ſummon me away</l>
               <l>I muſt confeſs it ſore doth grieve me.</l>
               <l>I can with the no longer ſtay:</l>
               <l>When we are parted, he thon true hearted</l>
               <l>thou wilt not change thy mind I know.</l>
               <l>From thée my favour, ſhall never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>though i muſt to <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When firſt I did behold thy feature,</l>
               <l>my ſenſes all were ſet on fire.</l>
               <l>Thy beauty bright, and comely Stature,</l>
               <l>which cauſed me for to admire:</l>
               <l>But fates prevent me, for to content thée;</l>
               <l>which fills my heart ſo full of woe;</l>
               <l>I cannot tarry, with thee to marry,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>for i muſt to <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long time I have béen true and conſtant,</l>
               <l>as thou thy ſelf didſt, always find.</l>
               <l>I never proved falſe one inſtant,</l>
               <l>nor never was to thée unkind:</l>
               <l>My dear believe me, and do not grieve me,</l>
               <l>ſince thou doſt ſee it muſt be ſo.</l>
               <l>My fortune I, will now go try,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>for i muſt to <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had I a thouſand pounds to leave thée.</l>
               <l>although it were in good red Gold.</l>
               <l>Not half ſo much it now would grieve me,</l>
               <l>to ſpeak the truth I may be bold:</l>
               <l>What ever thou requir'dſt of me,</l>
               <l>thou never heardſt me anſwer no;</l>
               <l>Therefore content thée do not preſent me</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>for i muſt to <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>TIs for Promotion and for Honour,</l>
               <l>that I muſt fail upon thée Flood,</l>
               <l>Il'e venture under <hi>Englands</hi> Banner;</l>
               <l>although I loſe my deareſt Blood:</l>
               <l>For unto danger I am no ſtranger,</l>
               <l>when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> minds aloud do blow,</l>
               <l>I'le not forget the my deareſt <hi>Betty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>though i muſt to <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>betty</hi> heard his Reſolution,</l>
               <l>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at he was ſo fully bent.</l>
               <l>Her ſenſes all were in Confuſion,</l>
               <l>and thus with ſorrow ſhe did lament:</l>
               <l>O ſtay quoth ſhe and do not venture,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aſt that thou break my heart with woe</l>
               <l>Leave not this City, but take ſome pitty,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And do not to <hi>Virginia</hi> go</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I prethee deareſt do not forſake me,</l>
               <l>thou knoweſt I love thee more then life.</l>
               <l>According to thy promiſe take me,</l>
               <l>and let me be thy Wedded wife:</l>
               <l>Leave bloody wars, and wounds and ſcars,</l>
               <l>to them who love did never know.</l>
               <l>Whilſt I will eaſe thee and ſtrive to pleaſe thee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>then do not to <hi>Virginia</hi> go</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if thou be reſolv'd to wander,</l>
               <l>and nothing can thy fancy turn.</l>
               <l>I'le march under the ſame Commander,</l>
               <l>and never ſtay at home to mourn:</l>
               <l>'Tis my deſire in Mans attire.</l>
               <l>thy Comrade to appear in ſhow.</l>
               <l>And day and night yield you delight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>as you unto <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O no quoth he, my deareſt Iewel,</l>
               <l>that may not be in any wiſe.</l>
               <l>Vpon the Seas are dangers Cruel,</l>
               <l>and many Storms ariſe:</l>
               <l>To ſtay at home then he contented,</l>
               <l>whilſt I do fight againſt my Foe.</l>
               <l>And ceaſe thy mourning, till my returning</l>
               <l>for i muſt to <hi>Virginia</hi> go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Take here this King which I do give thée,</l>
               <l>my deareſt and do not complain</l>
               <l>For with the ſame my heart I leave thee,</l>
               <l>untill that I return again:</l>
               <l>I hope here after for to embrace thee,</l>
               <l>then ſuffer not thoſe Tears to flow:</l>
               <l>For when I am abſent, I will be conſtant,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>although i do to</hi> Virginia <hi>go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo farewel my deareſt <hi>betty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>a thouſand times farwel my ſweet,</l>
               <l>I now afford the Kiſſes plenty,</l>
               <l>for to remember till we meet:</l>
               <l>If cruel Death of Life deprive us</l>
               <l>i'le meet the in the ſhades below,</l>
               <l>Where we together, ſhall be for ever,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>although i do to</hi> Virginia <hi>go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>betty</hi> ſaw her Lover parted,</l>
               <l>ſhe ſenſeleſs for a time remain'd,</l>
               <l>Being ſo kind and tender-hearted.</l>
               <l>at length her Spirits ſhe regain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</l>
               <l>And then a thouſand happy wiſhes,</l>
               <l>ſhe after ſent her Love to ſhow:</l>
               <l>Then home returned and there ſhe mourned</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>whilſt he did to</hi> Virginia <hi>go.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
